we have talked about the tensor flow API hierarchy.
API階層も確認しました
In the previous lesson, we talked about the directed acyclic graph, the DAG, and
セッションでの 有向非巡回グラフ（DAG）の
We said that a DAG consists of tensors and operations on those tensors.
DAGは テンソルと テンソルの演算で構成されます
Now, let's look in more detail at what tensors are.
ここでテンソルについて さらに詳しく見てみましょう
A tensor, remember, is a n-dimensional array of data.
テンソルはn次元のデータ配列です
When you create a tensor, you typically specify its shape.
テンソルを作成する際 通常は形状を指定しますが
Well occasionally, you will not specify the shape completely.
完全には指定しないこともあります
For example, the first element of the shape could be variable, but
形状の最初の要素は 変数にできますが
let's ignore that special case for now.
そうした特殊なケースは 今は無視します
So here, I'm creating a tf.constant(3).
ここでは tf.constant(3)を 作成しています
This is 0 rank tensor.
0ランクのテンソルです
It's just a number, it's a scalar.
単一の数値 つまりスカラーです
The shape, when you look at the tensor, debug output, will be simply ().
テンソルのデバッグ出力を見ると 形状は「( )」になります
It's 0 rank.
これが0ランクです
On the other hand, what if a past on the list 3, 5, 7 to tf.constant?
一方で「3, 5, 7」というリストを tf.constantに渡すと
Now, we have a one-dimensional tensor.
1次元テンソル つまりベクトルになります
So here, I'm passing a 2D array, 3, 5,
2行目に「4, 6, 8」を指定して
The shape of the resulting tensor is 2, 3,
テンソルの形状は 「2, 3」になりますが
2 rows, 3 columns, the rank is 2.
これは2行3列を意味し ランクは2です
You can think of a matrix as essentially a stack of 1D tensors.
行列は 1次元テンソルの 積み重ねと見なすことができます
The first tensor is a vector 3, 5, 7, and
最初のテンソルはベクトル「3, 5, 7」で
the second 1D tensor that's being stacked is a vector 4, 6, 8.
スタックの2番目の1次元テンソルは ベクトル「4, 6, 8」です
We can similarly create a 3D matrix by stacking 2D matrices,
同様に2次元行列を 積み重ねることで
one on top of each other.
3次元の行列を作成できます
You see me here stacking the 3, 5, 7, etc., matrix on top of the 1, 2, 3 matrix.
「3, 5, 7」で始まる行列を 「1, 2, 3」に積み重ねます
Since I stacked 2, 2 by 3 matrices,
2行3列の行列を 2つ積み重ねたので
the resulting shape of the tensor is 2, 2, 3.
テンソルの形状は 「2, 2, 3」になります
Of course, I can do the stacking in code instead,
これらのかっこを数えなくても
instead of counting all those parenthesis.
コードで積み重ねることができます
So here, x1 is a constant and it's constructed from a simple list 2, 3, 4.
ここでは「x1」が定数で 単純な「2, 3, 4」で構成されます
So that makes it a vector of length 3.
これは 長さ3のベクトルになります
x2 is constructed by stacking x1 on top of x1,
「x2」は「x1」に「x1」を 積み重ねて作成され
so that makes it a 2 by 3 matrix.
2行3列の行列になります
x3 is constructed by stacking four x2s on top of each other.
「x3」は4つの「x2」を 互いに積み重ねて作成されます
And since each x2 was a 2 by 3 matrix,
各「x2」は2行3列の 行列なので
this makes x3 a 3D tensor whose shape is 4 by 2 by 3.
「x3」は「4, 2, 3」の 3次元テンソルになります
x4 is constructed by stacking x3 on top of x3,
「x4」は「x3」に「x3」を 積み重ねて作成されます
so that makes it two of those 4 by 2 by 3 tensors,
「4, 2, 3」のテンソル 2つで構成される
So you can stack tensors on top of each other to create tensors of higher
積み重ねることで
You can also slice a tensor to pull out lower dimensional tensors.
また テンソルをスライスして
So here, what is the shape of x?
この場合「x」の形状は何でしょうか
It's 2 by 3.
「2, 3」 2行3列です
Now take a look at the code for y.
「y」のコードに注目してください
It's slicing x.
「x」をスライスしています
The colon indicates that we're getting all the rows, and
コロンは すべての行を取得することを示し
the one that indicates that we're getting just column one, which because
「1」は1列だけ取得することを意味します
Python is zero indexed, is actually the second column 01, so second column.
Pythonではゼロから数えるため 実際には2番目の列です
So when we evaluate y, we get the value of the second column for all the rows.
「y」を評価する際に すべての行で2列目の値を取得します
And that's why 5, 6 is being printed out.
そのため「5, 6」が出力されます
So quick quiz, what would x[1,
ここで質問です x[1, :] の値はどうなりますか
How about x[1, 0:2], what would that do?
x[1, 0:2]についてはどうでしょうか 実行するとどうなりますか
So answers?
答えは
When you do x[1, : ], you will get the second row.
x[1, : ]を実行すると 2行目を取得します
Remember zero indexing?
ゼロから数えるので
So one is the second row?
「1」は2行目です
And you will get all the columns.
すべての列を取得し
So we'll get [4, 6, 8].
[4, 6, 8]が得られます
So which columns will 0:2 pull?
では 0:2はどの列を抜き出しますか
Now, this is very similar to the x range function in Python.
これは Pythonのx range関数に 似ています
It means, start at 0 and go up 2, but not including 2.
0から開始して2つ進みますが 2は含みません
So this means, 0 and 1.
「0」と「1」という意味です
And this means that you will get both the rows, so it's actually the same thing.
これは 両方の行を取得することを意味するため
We will still get 4, 6, 8 on this data.
実際には同じ「4, 6, 8」が得られます
Once you have the data into a tensor,
データがテンソルに挿入されたら
you can take all that data and it can reshape the tensor.
すべてのデータを使って 形状を調整できます
So x is a 2D tensor, what's its shape?
「x」は2次元テンソルですが 形状は何でしょう
That's right, 2 by 3.
そう「2, 3」です
If I reshape it as 3, 2, what will happen?
形状を「3, 2」に変更すると どうなるでしょう
What I want is that, I want the six values in x, but
「x」に6個の値が必要ですが
I want them put into 3 rows and 2 columns.
それらを3行2列に配置することになります
So essentially, Python will read the input tensor row by row, and
基本的にPythonは行ごとに 入力テンソルを読み取り
put the numbers into the output tensor.
出力テンソルに数値を配置します
So it would pick the first two values and put it in the first row, so
最初の2つの値を 最初の行に配置します
we get 3 and 5.
「3」と「5」となります
The next two values, 7 and 4, will go in to the second row,
次の2つの値「7」と「4」が 2行目に入り
and the last two values, 6 and 8, go into the third row.
最後の「6」と「8」が 3行目に入ります
So that's what reshaping does.
形状の調整によって こうなります
We can reshape, and we can slice.
形状は調整も スライスも可能です
So here, I'm reshaping it to 3 by 2 as before, and
「3, 2」に変更して スライスすると
then I'm slicing it, so I'm getting only the second row and all the columns.
2行目のすべての列のみが 取得されます
And that's why I get 7, 4.
結果、「7, 4」が得られます